A Finding Aid to the William J. Eisenlord Photographs, 1953-1976, in the Archives of American Art AAA.eisewill
Archives of American Art
William J. Eisenlord photographs
1953-1976
AAA.eisewill
Archives of American Art
0.3 Linear feet
The photographs of San Francisco photographer William J. Eisenlord measure 0.3 linear feet and date from 1953-1976. Photographs depict the City Lights Bookstore of San Francisco, California and the exhibition opening of "Poets of the Cities" at the San Francisco Museum of Art in 1976. Also included are photographs of jazz and beat poetry performances taken by Ed Nyberg in 1957.
Eisenlord, William J., 1926-1997
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The William J. Eisenlord photographs were donated to the Archives of American Art in two installments, in 1976 and 1977, by William J. Eisenlord.
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection was digitized in 2011 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical/Historical note
William J. Eisenlord (1926-1997) worked as a photographer in San Francisco, California. He was an acquaintance of photographer, poet, and journalist Mark Green. Together with business partner Thayne Riggs, Eisenlord opened the Omnibus Gallery in Sacramento, California in 1980.
Scope and Contents note
The photographs of San Francisco photographer William J. Eisenlord measure 0.3 linear feet and date from 1953-1976. Photographs depict the City Lights Bookstore of San Francisco, California and the exhibition opening of "Poets of the Cities" at the San Francisco Museum of Art in 1976. Also included are photographs of jazz and beat poetry performances taken by Ed Nyberg in 1957.
City Lights Bookstore was a popular meeting ground for many people associated with the Beat literary movement in San Francisco. The collection includes one exterior window photograph of the bookstore taken the year of its founding in 1953, and fifteen interior photographs of the store taken circa 1959. The interior shots include images of bookstore founder Lawrence Ferlinghetti, bookstore manager Shigeyoshi Murao, and various customers browsing the stacks.
The photographs taken at the "Poets of the Cities" exhibition opening on January 30, 1976 at the San Francisco Museum of Art include notable figures Jack Micheline, Claes Oldenburg, James Broughton, Phil Linhares, Mark and Sally Green, Michael Larsen, Elizabeth Pomada, Ken deRoux, Peter and Minette LeBlanc, Jack Hirschman, Rolando Castellon, Knute Stiles, Michael and Joanna McClure, Byron Meyer, Peter Selz, Leo Castelli, George Herms, and Shirley and Wallace Berman.
Also included are ten photographs taken in 1957 by Ed Nyberg at The Jazz Cellar, a popular San Francisco beat nightclub. Notable figures include Kenneth Rexroth, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Grover Sales Jr., Sonny Wayne, and Bill Weisjahn.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 2 series:
Series 1: William J. Eisenlord Photographs, 1953-1976 (Box 1; 15 folders)
Series 2: Ed Nyberg Photographs, 1957 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Berman, Shirley; Berman, Wallace, 1926-1976; Broughton, James; Castelli, Leo; Castellón, Rolando; City Lights Bookstore. (San Francisco, Calif.) -- Photographs; DeRoux, Kenneth; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence; Green, Mark L., 1932-2004; Herms, George, 1935-; Hirschman, Jack, 1933-; Larsen, Michael, 1941-; LeBlanc, Peter, 1930-; Linhares, Philip E.; McClure, Michael; Micheline, Jack, 1929-1998; Nyberg, Ed; Oldenburg, Claes, 1929- -- Photographs; Pomada, Elizabeth; Rexroth, Kenneth, 1905-1982; San Francisco Museum of Art; Selz, Peter Howard, 1919-; Stiles, Knute, 1923-; Beat generation--California--San Francisco; Photographers--California--San Francisco; Photographs; Poets--Exhibitions--Photographs; San Francisco Calif.--Photographs
- William J. Eisenlord Photographs, 1953-1976; Series 1; 15 Folders Box 1
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  1.1: City Lights Bookstore, 1953-1959
  1.2: "Poets of the City" Exhibition Opening, 1976
  - City Lights Bookstore, 1953-1959; 1.1
    Scope and Contents note
    City Lights Bookstore was a popular meeting ground for many people associated with the Beat literary movement in San Francisco. The collection includes one exterior window photograph of the bookstore taken the year of its founding in 1953, and fifteen interior photographs of the store taken circa 1959. The interior shots include images of bookstore founder Lawrence Ferlinghetti, bookstore manager Shigeyoshi Murao, and various customers browsing the stacks.
    The subseries has been scanned in its entirety.
    - Photographs of City Lights Bookstore, Exterior, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      (Pictured are William Brothers, Cathy Furniss, William J. Eisenlord, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of City Lights Bookstore, Interior, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      (Pictured are Lawrence Ferlinghetti and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of City Lights Bookstore, Interior, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (Pictured are Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Shigeyoshi Murao and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of City Lights Bookstore, Interior, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Photographs of City Lights Bookstore, Interior, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Poets of the City" Exhibition Opening, 1976; 1.2
    The photographs taken at the "Poets of the Cities" exhibition opening on January 30, 1976 at the San Francisco Museum of Art include notable figures Jack Micheline, Claes Oldenburg, James Broughton, Phil Linhares, Mark and Sally Green, Michael Larsen, Elizabeth Pomada, Ken deRoux, Peter and Minette LeBlanc, Jack Hirschman, Rolando Castellon, Knute Stiles, Michael and Joanna McClure, Byron Meyer, Peter Selz, Leo Castelli, George Herms, and Shirley and Wallace Berman.
    - Index to "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Photographs, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Pictured are Jack Micheline, Claes Oldenburg, H. King, Bob Whyte, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (Pictured are James Broughton, Bob White, Dennis O'Leary, Sue Foley, H. King, Phil Linhares, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (Pictured are Barbara Wohl, Phil Linhares, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      (Pictured are Mark Green, Michael Larsen, Elizabeth Pomada, Ken deRoux, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      (Pictured are John Berguin, Minette and Peter LeBlanc, Kirby Ferlinghetti, Jack Hirschman, Rolando Castellon and his wife, Knute Stiles, Dana and Bob Johnson, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      (Pictured are H. King, Joanna McClure, Shigeyoshi Murao, Minette LeBlanc and her mother, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      (Pictured are Mrs. Nicholas Boyd, Mary Miles Ryan, Byron Meyer, H. King, Peter Selz, Leo Castelli, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      (Pictured are H. King, Peter Selz, Minette LeBlanc, E. Kaufman, Sally and Mark Green, and unidentified others)
    - Photographs of the "Poets of the Cities" Exhibition Opening, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      (Pictured are Shigeyoshi Murao, Michael McClure, George Herms, Shirley and Wallace Berman, and unidentified others)
- Ed Nyberg Photographs, 1957; Series 2
  This series consists of ten photographs taken in 1957 by Ed Nyberg at The Jazz Cellar, a popular San Francisco beat nightclub. Notable figures include Kenneth Rexroth, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Grover Sales Jr., Sonny Wayne, and Bill Weisjahn.
  The series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Photographs of Jazz and Poetry Performances at The Jazz Cellar, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    (Pictured are Kenneth Rexroth, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, Grover Sales Jr., Sonny Wayne, Bill Weisjahn, and unidentified others)